if you're like me and you dream of
building the next instagram twitter or
facebook there are two features your
application is for sure going to need
the first one is real time messaging
unicorns like tinder over instagram or
twitter they all have some sort of
direct messaging system and the apps
like slack twitch or youtube rely very
heavily in real time public chat rooms
the second feature is activity fits
which is something that apps like
instagram or twitter are literally built
upon if your app allows users to follow
each other and you want to show to your
users the posts and activities of the
people they follow you need an activity
feed or if you're building a
notifications tab where your users can
see that somebody like their photo or
somebody mentioned them on a comment you
need a notifications feed implementing
these two features by yourself real time
messaging and activity feeds it's
possible but not so easy for the chat
you need to code and maintain the
real-time servers that should be capable
of holding many websocket connections
open for all the people in the chat room
you also need to code all the logic to
handle channels messages private
channels reactions threads among many
other things and for the feeds you need
to code all the logic for follows on
follows likes mentions pagination fan
out so many things or you can save your
time and you can use stream instead a
stream is a backend as a service
platform that allows you to implement
real-time chat messaging and activity
feeds in record time and the best of all
is absolutely free for makers like you
and me companies like soundcloud strava
adobe master class and etoro among many
many others use a stream for real-time
chat messaging and activity feeds stream
also has sdks for vanilla javascript
react.js react native flutter android
ios unity and even unreal engine and if
that wasn't enough a stream also has a
collection of ui components that we can
use to save even more time when
implementing chats or activity feeds if
you want to get started right now click
on the link below to sign up for your
free maker account or keep watching
because to see how easy it is to work
with stream we are going to implement
our own real-time chat using the stream
chat api and the stream react chat
components now before we start i need to
warn you stream is going to blow your
mind after we sign up for stream and get
a free maker account we will create a
new app for this we have to select the
region we want the code and the data to
be next we're going to create a new
channel type with a channel type we can
customize the features the rules and the
permissions that our users will have
when using our chat stream comes with
very useful channel types already made
for us for example the live stream chat
comes pre-configured with some
permissions already that allow logged in
users to write in the chat but only
allows anonymous users to read the chat
or for example the messaging chat comes
with some pre-configuration that doesn't
allow guests to look at the chat only
registered users only thanks to channel
types we can also specify what are the
events that our users are going to be
subscribed to when creating a new
channel type all we have to do is write
the name and select the events that we
are interested on
an example of an event is a typing event
we should leave this on if we want our
users to know when someone is typing a
message like in slack or in messenger
for example we're going to leave all of
them on for now then we're going to
write down the permission rules for our
chat first we will allow the admin which
is us to do whatever we want and then
we're going to allow guest users to be
able to create channels write messages
react to messages upload files and send
links now we are done with the
configuration we can now go to our react
application first we have to install the
stream chat npm package then we're going
to grab our api key from the settings
page of our application and use it to
connect from our code then when our
application starts we're going to
connect to stream using a guest user
with a random id
after that we will now create or connect
to a channel with the channel type that
we created before we will give it a name
and we will save this channel in the
state
now that we are connected you will
install the ui react components that are
provided for us by stream for free all
we have to do is npm install a stream
chat react and then all we have left to
do is to render the components and this
is the mind-blowing part stream gives us
components like chat channel and window
that will render a chat window on the
channel that we are connected to if we
want to show a header on the channel to
display the name of the channel and to
display a count of how many people are
currently online all we have to do is
render the channel header component as
you can see we can see the result
immediately in our screen now if we want
to show a list of messages in our
channel all we have to do is render the
message list component now because we
don't have any messages yet we have to
allow our users to write the messages
instead of creating an input manually
and doing all the code by ourselves all
we have to do is render the message
input component and boom that's it as
you can see that gives us an input that
works out of the box we can now send
messages and even upload files now when
all your users connect to our chat they
will see the list of previous messages
they will know when other users are
typing and they will even be able to
react to messages with emojis and this
is all because we render the right
components in the right places and if
that wasn't enough if we wanted our
users to be able to open threads in
messages the ways like that for example
all we have to do is render the thread
component just by doing that the users
can now talk in threads how easy was
that it's crazy we just made our own
slack clone with writing almost no
javascript at all and zero lines of css
the string chat react components are
super customizable as well here you can
see all the components you can use if
you want to modify the default look of
the message ui they are also full of
props that you can change and you can
even add class names if you want to
change the css directly and of course
you don't always have to use the stream
chat react components you can use your
own components with the chat api
thankfully the stream api is very
intuitive for example if you wanted to
send a message to the channel using code
and not the react stream components then
you can just do channel that send
message that's very easy to remember or
if you wanted to listen for new messages
in your channel all you have to do is
channel on new message or for example if
you wanted to add a reaction to a
message using your custom emojis all you
have to do is run channel send reaction
and the name of your reaction now let's
take a look at activity streams and see
how we would go about building a feed
instagram style for activity streams we
need a server from the server is from
where you will add the notifications to
the inbox of the users or activities to
their feeds on the server side first we
get a user token we do this to control
who can read the feed and notifications
in our front after we have our token
then we get a feed for our user
then in the server side when an event
happens we will add an activity to the
feed of our user we can also make our
user follow someone else now if for
example we were building a react native
application all we would have to do is
use the expo activity feed package that
a stream provides for free this package
has components that will allow us to
render our activity feeds doing
something like this the expo activity
feed package comes with like buttons
inputs link previews and even real-time
update notifications literally
everything you would need to build your
own social network as you can see a
stream is such a time saver doing what
we just did by ourselves we take us a
longer time thanks to stream we were
able to implement a real-time chat and
activity feeds in a matter of minutes
and our chat came with features like
private channels public channels message
reactions with emojis notification of
typing threads incredible now the good
news is that you can use a stream today
the free for makers account gives you
free and full access to the chat api for
up to 2 000 users per month and it gives
you full and free access to the feeds
api for up to 9 million feed updates per
month
click on the link below to sign up today
thank you to stream for sponsoring this
video and thank you for watching this
video let me know in the comments if you
would like to see a full tutorial on
stream using the chat api to build our
own slack clone or if you would like me
to use the feed api to build our own
twitter or instagram and that's it for
this video what do you think of stream
have you heard about stream do you want
to learn more about stream have you used
the stream let me know in the comments
i'm going to be looking at them right
now thank you so much for watching as
always stay happy stay free eat kimchi
i'm zamida san angelo see you on the
next one bye
[Music]